Guide to the Wesleyan Student Assembly Records, 1969 - 2005
Wesleyan Student Assembly Records, 1969 - 2005
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University. Wesleyan Student Assembly.
2000-64
11.4
21
The Wesleyan Student Assembly (WSA) was formed in 1978. It is the legislative and deliberative student body at Wesleyan University.
The Wesleyan Student Assembly Records include minutes, subject files, memoranda, reports, publications, flyers, and other materials related to the student government of Wesleyan University. Topics include campus speakers and visitors, facilities, offices and buildings, courses, departments, and issues involving professors and curriculum. The Administrative Files series is not processed, but a general listing of its contents is included.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given by the Wesleyan Student Assembly in 2000, 2001, and 2005.
Historical Note
The following historical note was taken from the WSA's website, http://www.wesleyan.edu/wsa/about/history.htm, on 21 June 2006.
The Wesleyan Student Assembly (WSA) is the legislative and deliberative body of the Wesleyan College Body. The WSA is comprised of 37 members and consists of nine standing committees: the Executive Committee, Coordinating Committee, Community Outreach Committee, Educational Policy Committee, Finance and Facilities Committee, Student Affairs Committee, Student Budget Committee, Independent Projects Committee, Student Trustees Committee and the Student Institutional Advisory Priorities Committee. The WSA responsibilities include allocating the College Body Tax to the 170+ student groups, meeting regularly with President Bennet, serving on the standing committees of the Board of Trustees, affecting academic and non-academic policy and improving Wesleyan-Middletown relations. The WSA maintains its offices at 190 High St. Cari Macdermott served as the WSA office coordinator from 1978 until her retirement in the spring of 2005. She was replaced by Lisa Hendrix, the new WSA office coordinator.
Student government originated as the College Body Senate in 1903. "The College Body of Wesleyan University" was formed in 1963 in response to a desire for better organization and was directed by the College Body Committee, comprised of five elected undergraduates. In 1975, the Wesleyan Students' Union was to fill the need for an organization to lobby specifically on behalf of student interests. A $1 membership was required. In 1978, 89% of the voting population approved a campus-wide referendum and the Wesleyan Student Assembly was formed. The Assembly was comprised of seven standing committees with 45 members serving during the fall term and 38 members during the spring term. Membership was distributed across the geographic boundaries of the campus stretching from In-Town to Butterfield.
The WSA has undergone a number of changes in composition throughout its history. In 1980, the Assembly had 37 members, in 1981 the membership was 27 members. The Assembly was again altered in 1984 to 28 members and persisted in this form until 1992 when the organization was expanded to 40 members. Representation has been changed from geographically based to year based and the leadership was shifted from the Coordinator position to a President, Vice-President format during the 1990's. In 1997, the WSA underwent its last iteration and now stands at 37 members.
The WSA enjoys a storied history of successes, reforms and restructurings as well as dramatic resignations and heated debate. In 1994, the Assembly experienced the "comedy of errors" when WSA elections were invalidated when an inadequate number of representatives were elected. In 1998, the absence of funding for the Film Board sparked the Film Series Controversy. Over the previous two academic years, the Assembly has played an integral role in the University's recent efforts at curricular renewal and reform of graduation requirements as well as influencing party policy, residential life issues and supporting efforts at responsible investing.
Collection Overview
The Wesleyan Student Assembly Records include minutes, subject files, memoranda, reports, publications, flyers, and other materials related to the student government of Wesleyan University. Topics include campus speakers and visitors, facilities, offices and buildings, courses, departments, and issues involving professors and curriculum. The Administrative Files series is not processed, but a general listing of its contents is included.
Collection Arrangement
Series 1. Minutes (Acc. 2000-64)
Series 2. Subject Files (Acc. 2001-41)
Series 3. Administrative Files (Acc. 2001-42, Acc. 2005-17, 2005-96)
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Wesleyan Student Assembly.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Presidents.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Administration.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Curricula.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Student government.; College student government--United States.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Buildings.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Minutes, 1978-2005 (Accession 2000-64)
  Consists of minutes of WSA meetings.
  - 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1979-1980 (Folder 2)
  - 1981-1982 (Folder 3)
  - 1982-1983 (Folder 4)
  - 1983-1984 (Folder 5)
  - 1984-1985 (Folder 6)
  - 1985-1986 (Folder 7)
  - 1989-1990 (Folder 8)
  - 1999-2000 (Folder 9)
  - 2000-2001 (Folder 10-11)
  - 2001-2002 (Folder 12)
  - 2004-2005 (Folder 13)
- Series 2. Subject Files, 1969-2001 (Accession 2001-41)
  Included are campus and outside correspondence, clippings, events posters, photographs, and memos documenting the WSA's involvement in campus issues and activities and occasional state or local legislative policymaking. File subjects include campus speakers and visitors, facilities, offices and buildings, courses, departments, and issues involving professors and curriculum. Files of extensive coverage include: divestment; Howard Bernstein; financial aid; Residential Life Task Force; sexual harrassment and assult; and the Student Budget Committee. The arrangement is alphabetical by subject.
  - Academic Planning Committee (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Accreditation (Folder 3)
  - Admissions Reports (Folder 4)
  - Adult Students (Folder 5)
  - Affirmative Action (Folder 6)
  - Afro-Am Studies (Folder 7)
  - Aid-Blind Admissions (Folder 8-9)
  - Alcohol Policy (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alumni (Folder 2)
  - Asian Alums (Folder 3)
  - American Studies (Folder 4)
  - Anthropology Dept. (Folder 5)
  - Area Coordinators (Folder 6)
  - Art Dept. (Folder 7)
  - Astronomy Dept. (Folder 8)
  - Athletics (Folder 9)
  - Attendance Policy--WSA (Folder 10)
  - Bail Policy and Contract (Folder 11)
  - Howard Bernstein (Folder 12)
  - BGLAD (Folder 13)
  - Biology Dept. (Folder 14)
  - Board of Trustees (General) (Folder 15-16)
  - Budget Advisory Committee (Folder 17)
  - Budget Reports (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Calendar (Folder 2)
  - Campus Center (Folder 3)
  - Career Planning Center (Folder 4-5)
  - Carepackages.com (Folder 6)
  - Center for Fine Arts (Folder 7)
  - William Chace (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chemistry Dept. (Folder 2)
  - Class/Dept. Enrollment (Folder 3-4)
  - Classics Dept. (Folder 5)
  - Cognitive Science (Folder 6)
  - Colin Committee (Folder 7)
  - College of Letters (Folder 8)
  - College of Social Studies (Folder 9)
  - Committee on Human Rights and Relations (Folder 10)
  - Computers (Folder 11)
  - Conferences (Student) (Folder 12)
  - Dance Dept. (Folder 13)
  - Davidson Art Center (Folder 14)
  - Dean's Office (Folder 15)
  - Dining and Food Service (Folder 16)
  - Dining Task Force (Folder 17)
  - Divestment - General (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Divestment - Social Implications Sub-Committee (Folder 5)
  - Divestment - Sit-In, April 1988 (Folder 6)
  - Drug Policy and Controversy (Folder 7)
  - Earth & Environmental Sciences Dept. (Folder 8)
  - East Asian Studies (Folder 9)
  - Economics Dept. (Folder 10)
  - Education Committee - General (Folder 11)
  - Education Committee - Trustees Committee, 1987-1989, and Tenure Decision (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Education Committee, 1978-1979 (Folder 2)
  - Education Committee, 1979-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Education Committee, 1981-1983 (Folder 4)
  - Educational Policy Committee Minutes (Folder 5-6)
  - Educational Studies Program (Folder 7)
  - Educational Philosophy (Folder 8)
  - Elections and Appointments (Folder 9)
  - English Dept. (Folder 10)
  - Facilities Committee (Folder 11)
  - Faculty Compensation (Folder 12)
  - Faculty Meetings (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Faculty, Minority (Folder 2)
  - Farrakahn (Folder 3)
  - Fayerweather Survey/Space Needs Report (Folder 4)
  - Film Series (Folder 5-7)
  - Financial Aid (Folder 8-9)
  - Financial Planning Committee (Folder 10)
  - Financial Planning Committee (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Fire Bombing/Racial Tension, Spring 1990 (Folder 2)
  - Flag Burning (Folder 3)
  - Fraternities Co-education (Folder 4)
  - Freeman Center Sports Complex (Folder 5)
  - Freshman Integrated Program (Folder 6)
  - Freshman Letter Fall (WSA) (Folder 7)
  - Gay Rights (Folder 8)
  - General Education (Folder 9)
  - G.L.A. Task Force (Folder 10)
  - Geographic Rep. Report (Folder 11)
  - German Dept. (Folder 12)
  - Government Dept. (Folder 13)
  - Graduate Liberal Studies Program (Folder 14)
  - Group Tutorials (Folder 15)
  - Grants (outside faculty) (Folder 16)
  - Nick Haddad (Folder 17)
  - Harrington Lodge (Folder 18)
  - Health Services (Folder 19)
  - History Dept. (Folder 20)
  - Honors and General Education (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Honor System (Folder 2)
  - Housing (Folder 3)
  - Human Rights and Relations Commission (Folder 4)
  - Impeachment Warning/Form Letter (Folder 5)
  - Insider's Guide to Wesleyan (Folder 6)
  - Investments Committee (Folder 7)
  - Latin-American Studies Program (Folder 8)
  - Leave of Absence/Sabbaticals (Folder 9)
  - Legal Problems/Litigation (Folder 10)
  - Leonard Prize (Folder 11)
  - Libraries (Folder 12)
  - Linguistics Program (Folder 13)
  - Math Dept. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Majors Committee (Folder 2)
  - Molecular Biology & Biochemistry Dept. (Folder 3)
  - Music Dept. (Folder 4)
  - Nuclear Freeze Issues (Folder 5)
  - Off Campus Housing (Folder 6)
  - Olin Dedication Party (Folder 7)
  - Orientation (Folder 8)
  - Over-Subscription (Folder 9)
  - Philosophy Dept. (Folder 10)
  - Physical Education (Folder 11)
  - Physics Dept. (Folder 12)
  - Planning Report, 1975-1980 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Preregistration (Folder 2-3)
  - Presidential Search Committee (Folder 4)
  - Psychology Dept. (Folder 5)
  - Public Affairs Center (Folder 6)
  - Public Safety (Folder 7)
  - Racism and Race Relations (Folder 8)
  - Jordan Rau (Folder 9)
  - Religion Dept. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Reproductive Rights (Folder 2)
  - Residential Life Task Force (Folder 3-4)
  - Reunion/Commencement (Folder 5)
  - Romance Languages Dept. (Folder 6)
  - Russian Dept. (Folder 7)
  - Science in Society Program (Folder 8)
  - Sesquicentennial (Folder 9)
  - Sexual Harrassment & Assault (Folder 10)
  - Sexual Harrassment & Assault (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Sexual Abuse Policies Task Force (Folder 2)
  - SIPAC (Folder 3)
  - Social Events (Folder 4)
  - Sloan Grant (Folder 5)
  - Sociology Dept. (Folder 6)
  - Solomen Amendment (Folder 7)
  - Student Affairs Committee (Folder 8)
  - Student Affairs Committee, 1994-1995 (Folder 9)
  - Student Budget Committee (Folder 10)
  - Student Empowerment Rally (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Student Judiciary Board (Folder 2)
  - Student Planning Committee (Folder 3)
  - Teacher Evaluations (Folder 4)
  - Teaching Assistants and Apprentices (Folder 5)
  - Telephone System (Folder 6)
  - Tenure (Folder 7)
  - Theater Department (Folder 8)
  - Transfer Credit (Folder 9)
  - Tuition (Folder 10)
  - University Courses (Folder 11)
  - University Ministry (Folder 12)
  - University Plan, March 1992 (Folder 13)
  - Vice President Search (Folder 14)
- Series 3. Administrative Files, 1979-2001 (Accessions 2001-42, 2005-17, 2005-96)
  The Administrative Files are arranged by their accession numbers. Materials within each accession have not been processed, but a general listing of the contents is provided.
  - Accession 2001-42
    The contents of this accession are from circa 1979-1986.
    - WSA Bulletin (Box 16)
    - Constitution and Amendments
    - Wesleyan Student Union
    - Wesleyan University Press
    - Whitebook Responses (4 folders)
    - Whitebook
    - Women's Studies Prog.
    - Withdrawal Policy
    - Academic Planning Group
    - Academic Planning Committee
    - Trustee Committees and Divestments
    - Public Relations/Student Communications
    - Student Affairs Committee
    - Educational Policy Committee (Box 17)
    - Gay and Lesbian Issues
    - Constitutional Reform
    - Financial Aid and Tuition
  - Accession 2005-17
    The contents of this accession are from circa 1986-2001.
    - Memos, Reports, 1991-1993 (Box 18)
    - Financial Binder, 1999-2000
    - Binder - Minutes, 2000-2001
    - Binder, 1986-1987
    - Folder - general institutional documents, circa 1992-1994 (Box 19)
    - Folder - SCSG, circa 1992-1993
    - Binder - Theard, 1989-1990
    - Binder - CC 93-94 Coordinator, 1993-1994
    - Binder, 1987-1988
    - Binder - 1988-1989, Eric Greene, Coordinator, 1988-1989 (Box 20)
    - Binder - CC 93-94 Jin's, 1993-1994
    - Binder, 1990-1991
    - Binder - CSA, Connecticut Student Association, 1986
  - Accession 2005-96
    - Film flyers (Box 21)
    - Speaker flyers
    - Student publications